--- ##midterm test past paper ---

--- ##midterm test past paper ---
PREFACE
ข้อสอบชุดนี้เป�นแนวข้อสอบรายวิชา 3000113 MED BIOCHEM/NUTRI จากความทรงจําของ
MDCU79 โดยที่ทางผู้จัดทําได้ทําการเติมเต็มข้อมูลข้อสอบจากที่จํามาให้ครบถ้วนมากยิ่งขึ้นใน
หลาย ๆ ข้อแต่ใจความของข้อสอบยังคงเดิม ทําให้ข้อสอบนั้นเสมือนจริงมากยิ่งขึ้น แต่หากมี
ข้อผิดพลาดใด ๆ ที่พบในข้อสอบฉบับนี้ ทางผู้จัดทําก็ขออภัยมา ณ ที่นี้
ในหลักสูตร 2567 นั้นมีการย่อเนื้อหาของรายวิชานี้อยู่ในรายวิชา 3050108 CELL BIO
BIOCHEM โดยที่มีเนื้อหาบางส่วนที่โดนตัดออก บางส่วนที่ย้ายไปอยู่ในรายวิชาอื่น ๆ และอาจมี
เนื้อหาบางส่วนที่เพิ่มเติมขึ้นมาใหม่ ดังนั้นโปรดใช้แนวข้อสอบฉบับนี้อย่างมีวิจารณญาณ
ทางผู้จัดทําขอขอบคุณเพื่อน ๆ MDCU79 ทุกคนที่ร่วมกับจําแนวข้อสอบของรายวิชานี้เพื่อให้เป�น
แนวทางในการเตรียมตัวสอบของน้อง ๆ เพื่อให้ได้เข้าใจหลักของชีวเคมีได้ดียิ่งขึ้น และขอขอบคุณ
อาจารย์ในภาควิชาชีวเคมีและสรีรวิทยาที่ได้มอบความรู้ในเรื่องหลักชีวเคมีและโภชนาการเพื่อ
นําไปใช้ในระดับที่สูงขึ้นและใช้ในการแพทย์จริง ๆ ในอนาคตต่อไป
ขอให้น้อง ๆ โชคดีกับการเรียนและการสอบในป� 1 ทุกคน
ทีมงานฝ�ายวิชาการชั้นป�ที่ 1 MDCU79
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
CHAPTER 1
Principle of metabolism and nutrition / nutrients and energy
needed across lifespan
1. Which of the following is NOT a health benefit of the mediterranean diet over the
American diet?
A. Higher in fiber
B. Lower in red meat
C. Higher in oleic acid
D. Higher in whole grains
E. Lower in EPA and DHA
2. Which of the following is the LEAST likely approach for personal nutrition?
A. Biomarker data from blood samples
B. Consultation with nutrition specialist
C. Consumption of fruits’ peels
D. Diets designed for kidney disease patients
E. Analysis of gut bacteria in stool samples
3. Which amino acids are essential for children?
A. Arginine Histidine Lysine
B. Alanine Histidine Leucine
C. Tyrosine Methionine Valine
D. Isoleucine Threonine Proline
E. Isoleucine Phenylalanine Cysteine
4. The main objective of macronutrients consumption?
A. To biosynthesize complex compound essential for cellular and tissue
structure
B. To dispose of toxic substances and leftovers
C. To produce heat for maintaining body temperature
D. To produce energy as ATP
E. To stabilize and maintain neural and hormonal homeostasis
5. Which pair of food has the highest amount of AGEs?
A. B. C. D. Beef steak with low fat milk
Fried meat with high sugar drink
Vegetable salad with orange juice
Grilled chicken with baked potatoes
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
CHAPTER 2
Nutrition for health promotion & NCDs prevention
1. 2. 3. 4. 5. Consumption of which of the following could lead to an increased rate of NCD?
A. Artificial sweeteners
B. Artificial preservative
C. Synthetic fiber
D. Trans fat
E. High protein
Which is NOT in the 2030 sustainable development goals (SDGs)?
A. Good health and well-being
B. Climate action
C. Peace, justice and strong institutions
D. Better air quality
E. Use traditional energy source
Which type of health promotion should be promoted in patients with end-stage
lung cancer?
A. Primary health promotion
B. Secondary health promotion
C. Tertiary health promotion
D. Quaternary health promotion
E. Individualized health promotion
Which of the following is not a characteristic of a ketogenic diet?
A. High unsaturated fat
B. Moderate protein
C. High glycemic index
D. Most calories come from fat
E. Low carbohydrate content
Lack of physical activity is a significant risk factor for cardiovascular mortality.
The appropriate and effective approach involves engaging in:
A. B. C. D. E. Moderate exercise for 60 minutes per week
Moderate exercise for 90 minutes per week
Moderate exercise for 150 minutes per week
Vigorous exercise for 120 minutes per week
Vigorous exercise for 150 minutes per week
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
6. An athlete has dryness and redness on his skin while he is running. He also
doesn’t seem to be sweating. What should he drink to alleviate his condition?
A. Milk
B. Cola
C. Water
D. Yogurt
E. Bicarbonate drink
CHAPTER 3
Carbohydrate metabolism
1. A neonate shows symptoms of vomiting and diarrhea after breastfeeding.
Physical examination shows jaundice and hepatomegaly. Which of the following
enzymes may defect in this patient?
A. Aldolase B
B. Fructokinase
C. Galactokinase
D. Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase
E. Sorbitol dehydrogenase
2. 10 glucose molecules enter the cellular respiration process and generates 8
lactate molecules via anaerobic respiration and CO2 36 molecules via glycerol-3-
phosphate shuttle of aerobic respiration. How many molecules of ATP will be
gained?
A. 120
B. 224
C. 228
D. 236
E. 248
3. A patient’s PEPCK has been blocked. What can still be used for
gluconeogenesis?
A. Glycerol
B. Pyruvate
C. Lactate
D. Alanine
E. Leucine
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
4. 5. 6. 7. 8. What happens when glucose-6-phosphate is deficient?
A. Hyperglycemia
B. C. D. E. Accumulation of glycogen in liver
Accumulation of unbranched glycogen in liver
Accumulation of glycogen in muscle
Accumulation of unbranched glycogen in muscle
A 40-year-old man was diagnosed with diabetes mellitus. A novel treatment for
diabetes mellitus has been discovered by giving fructose-2,6-bisphosphate to
the patient. Fructose-2,6-bisphosphate given stimulates the activity of which
enzyme?
A. Phosphofructokinase – 1
B. Pyruvate kinase
C. Pyruvate carboxylase
D. Phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase (PEPCK)
E. Fructose-1,6-bisphosphatase
A patient presents in the emergency room with signs of alcoholism. Which
metabolites are increased in this patient?
A. Malic acid
B. Oxaloacetic acid
C. Pyruvic acid
A patient has been administered with primaquine but then comes back to the
doctor with signs of anemia. This means that primaquine inhibits which enzyme?
A. Phosphofructokinase-1
B. Galactokinase
C. Glucose-6-phosphatase
D. Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase
E. Transketolase
From the graph, what is A and B?
A. B. C. D. E. A = Skeletal muscle, B = Pancreatic cell
A = Skeletal muscle, B = Hepatocyte
A = Adipose tissue, B = Skeletal muscle
A = Renal cell, B =Hepatocyte
A = Renal cell, B = Adipose tissue
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
9. A patient comes with blurred vision and has cataracts. He also has hypertension
and diabetes mellitus type II. What is the cause of cataracts in this patient?
A. Sorbitol
B. Mannitol
C. Galactitol
D. Xylitol
E. Ribulose
10. A patient comes in to inject glucagon. What happens after being injected with
glucagon?
A. Glycogenesis
B. Glycogenolysis
C. Lipid synthesis
D. Glycolysis
E. Protein synthesis
CHAPTER 4
Lipid metabolism I-III (อ.ชาลิสา + อ.สิทธิศักดิ์)
1. 2. A patient has been administered with bile acid sequestrants. What is the
consequence of consuming this type of medication?
A. Stimulates cholesterol 7α-hydroxylase
B. Stimulates ACAT
C. Inhibits LCAT
D. Inhibits HMG-CoA reductase
E. Stimulates HMG-CoA synthase
A patient comes to the doctor due to worsening asthma. She seems to be
overusing beta agonists and corticosteroid medications and the symptoms didn’t
improve. Drug A is administered to alleviate the symptoms. What is the
mechanism of drug A?
A. Acts as leukotriene receptor antagonist
B. Inhibits COX-1
C. Inhibit COX-2
D. Inhibit phospholipase A2
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
3. Usually, patients with abetalipoproteinemia also presents with failure of blood
clotting. What is the underlying pathophysiology?
A. LDL receptor deficiency
B. Inhibits COX
C. D. Inhibits the production of thromboxane
Inhibits the production of arachidonic acid
4. 5. 6. A patient presents with these laboratory test values:
Total cholesterol 250 mg/dl Triglyceride 200 mg/dl What seems to be impaired?
A. Cholesterol synthesis by liver
B. Cholesterol transport from tissue to liver
C. Cholesterol absorption by enterocyte
D. Triglyceride production by enterocyte
E. Triglyceride transport from intestine to tissue
HDL 10 mg/dl
A 1-year-old child comes to see the doctor with his mother, which complains
about his severe mental retardation. Further examination indicates
splenomegaly and hepatomegaly. His laboratory examination reveals an
abnormally high amount of sphingomyelin. What is the disease the child
presents
A. Tay-Sach syndrome
B. Gaucher syndrome
C. Neumann-Pick syndrome
D. Abetalipoproteinemia
E. Hyperchylomicronemia
The laboratory findings of a patient reveal severe hypoglycemia, but it is not
known whether it is caused from glycolysis/gluconeogenesis problems or
medium-chain fatty acyl CoA dehydrogenase (MCAD) deficiency. Which findings
may confirm that it is caused from MCAD deficiency?
A. High dicarboxylic acid in blood
B. High acylcarnitine in blood
C. High methylmalonic acid in blood
D. High beta-hydroxybutyrate in blood
E. High lactic acid in blood
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
7. 8. Which lipoprotein is reduced in patients with hypercholesterolemia who take
low-carb diet?
A. LDL
B. IDL
C. HDL
D. VLDL
E. Chylomicron
A person is suffering from a disease and can’t eat anything for 2 days. Explain
the metabolic state of the liver in this person.
Choice Fatty acid synthesis Ketone bodies synthesis Ketone bodies oxidation
A. + + 0
B. 0 + +
C. 0 0 +
D. 0 + 0
E. + 0 0
9. Fill the sentence in the blanks from left to right:
“The lipids we’ve taken are emulsified by ______ and then are packed into
______ in intestinal cells. The lipids are then transported to the bloodstream by
”
_____.
A. Bile, Cholesterol, VLDL
B. Bile, Triglyceride, Chylomicrons
C. Bile, Triglyceride, VLDL
D. Lipase, Cholesterol, VLDL
E. Lipase, Triglyceride, Chylomicrons
10. A patient presents with yellow plagues on the upper eyelids like in this picture.
Laboratory findings reveal the cholesterol and LDL level of 300 mg/dL and 200
mg/dL, respectively. What is defected in this patient?
A. Apo B-48
B. Apo E
C. Apo C-II
D. Apo B-100
E. LPL
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
CHAPTER 5
Eating behavior & obesity
1. 2. 3. What is the most accurate factor for determining NCDs?
A. Waist circumference
B. BMI
C. Skin fold thickness
D. Weight to height ratio
E. Weight
How can cannabis increase appetite?
A. Stimulate Neuropeptide Y
B. Increase serum Ghrelin
C. Inhibit satiety center of hypothalamus
D. Increase activity of hunger center of hypothalamus
E. Inhibit MC4 receptor
A scientist causes lesions in the lateral hypothalamus of a mouse. What will
happen to the mouse?
A. Lower appetite and very thin body
B. Higher appetite and obese
C. Lower appetite and obese
D. Higher appetite and very thin body
E. Normal appetite but obese
CHAPTER 6
Dietary supplementation
1. Which substance is used illegally in dietary supplements for reducing weight?
A. Amphetamine
B. Sibutramine
2. Which bacteria must be checked in the dietary supplements before getting
verified?
A. Salmonella Typhi
B. Clostridium Difficile
C. Vibrio Cholerae
D. Escherichia coli
E. Staphylococcus aureus
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
3. Which organization is responsible for over-advertisements of dietary
supplements in Thailand?
A. Ministry of Commerce
B. Ministry of Public Health
C. Food and Drug Administration
D. Office of the Consumer Protection Board
E. Office of Judicial and Legal Affairs
CHAPTER 7
Nucleotide metabolism
1. What is the mechanism of acyclovir?
A. HSV virus analog
B. Inhibit reverse transcriptase
C. Inhibit DNA polymerase
D. Inhibit HSV-thymidine kinase
E. Nucleoside analog
2. A patient presents with hyperuricemia and mental retardation and is diagnosed
with Lesch-Nyhan syndrome, a disease characterized with the defect of a certain
enzyme. What is the substrate of the enzyme?
A. Guanine
B. Uridine
C. Adenosine
D. Inosine
E. Cytosine
3. A 4-year-old patient presented with megaloblastic anemia. Urinary
demonstrated the formation of the orotate crystal. The laboratory result shows a
normal level of vitamin B12 and folate. Which of the following enzyme is most
likely defective in this patient?
A. Aspartate transcarbamoylase
B. HGPRT
C. XMP aminase
D. Carbamoyl phosphate synthase II
E. UMP synthase
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
4. 5. 6. 7. 8. Metabolism of which ribonucleotide produces a Krebs cycle intermediate?
A. dTTP
B. dATP
C. dCTP
D. dUTP
E. dGTP
PABA analog is one type of antibiotics. Which process is affected from this drug?
A. De novo purine synthesis
B. De novo pyrimidine synthesis
C. Purine salvage
D. Pyrimidine salvage
E. Purine degradation
Glutamine is used in conversion of uridine to which molecule?
A. ATP
B. TTP
C. CTP
D. GTP
E. UTP
A 10-month-old boy was brought to a hospital by his mother. His blood tests
show an absence of T cell and B cell. Based on several examinations, he is
diagnosed with Severe Combined Immunodeficiency (SCID). Which of the
following enzyme is most likely defective in this patient?
A. UMP synthase
B. AMP deaminase
C. Thymidine kinase
D. PRPP amidotransferase
E. HGPRT
A patient has been administered with a drug that inhibits RNP reductase. What is
the function of the enzyme?
A. B. C. D. E. Inhibits de novo purine synthesis
Inhibits formation of ribose from deoxyribose
Inhibits formation of deoxyribose from ribose
Inhibits degradation pathway of nucleotides
Inhibits salvage pathway of nucleotides
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
CHAPTER 8
Amino acid metabolism
1. A caveman hasn’t eaten any food during the past four days. Which nutrient will
be used as the main energy resource for intestinal cells?
A. Leucine
B. Alanine
C. Glutamine
D. Tryptophan
E. Serine
2. A girl is born with unusually fair skin, white hair and red iris. Which enzyme is
probably dysfunctional?
A. Glutathione reductase
B. Glutathione oxidase
C. Phenylalanine hydroxylase
D. Tyrosinase
E. Homogentisate oxidase
3. A patient’s laboratory findings indicate high levels of phenylalanine but low
levels of dopamine, serotonin and epinephrine. However, the patient’s urine
doesn’t have a musty odor. How should the patient be treated?
A. Avoid phenylalanine diet
B. Tetrahydrobiopterin supplements
C. Tyrosine supplements
D. Serotonin injection
4. What substance doesn’t need methionine for synthesis in the metabolic
pathway?
A. Carnitine
B. Creatine
C. Dopamine
D. Epinephrine
E. Cysteine
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
5. 6. 7. 8. 9. Which amino acid doesn’t give acetyl CoA when metabolized?
A. Isoleucine
B. Valine
C. Tryptophan
D. Lysine
E. Leucine
A patient comes to the emergency room from coma due to encephalopathy.
Blood tests reveal high ammonia due to urea cycle defect. Which amino acid is
accumulated in the blood of this patient?
A. Glutamate
B. Glycine
C. Arginine
D. Alanine
E. Phenylalanine
Which amino acid is not essential in adults due to maturation of gut microbiome?
A. Tryptophan
B. Arginine
C. Histidine
D. Tyrosine
E. Valine
A patient complains about having a bad rash around the neck, profuse diarrhea
and loss of memory. Further diagnosis reveals that she has problems with
tryptophan transport in the small intestine. In addition to tryptophan
supplementation, which vitamin should be administered with?
A. Vitamin B1
B. Vitamin B2
C. Vitamin B3
D. Vitamin B6
E. Vitamin B12
A patient comes to the doctor with the chief complaint of weakness. Laboratory
results reveal macrocytic anemia in the blood while the methylmalonic acid level
in the urine is normal. Which substance should be decreased in the blood?
A. Cysteine
B. Thymine
C. Threonine
D. Adenosine
E. Histidine
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
10. A patient comes to see the doctor during fasting. Blood test and further analysis
reveals metabolic acidosis, high levels of alanine and alanine transaminase (ALT)
in the blood. Which pathway is disturbed in this patient?
A. Cahill cycle
B. Cori cycle
C. Urea cycle
D. Krebs cycle
E. Glycolysis
CHAPTER 9
Metabolism of heme & macromolecules
1. Which physiologic process does the cell use to control heme synthesis?
A. Control iron synthesis
B. Control succinyl CoA synthesis
C. Control ferrochelatase enzyme
D. Control PBG synthesis
E. Control ALA synthesis
2. Mucopolysaccharidosis occurs due to insufficient glycosaminoglycan (GAG)
degradation. Which substance causes GAG degradation?
A. Apoptosome complex
B. Ubiquitin E3 ligase
C. Peroxisomal enzymes
D. Lysosomal enzymes
E. Proteasome complex
3. A baby with jaundice comes to the doctor with light clay color stool and milk tea
urine. Blood test shows elevated direct bilirubin. What might be the cause?
A. Lead poisoning
B. Bile duct obstruction
C. Vitamin B6 defect
D. Liver dysfunction
E. Uroporphyrinogen decarboxylase deficiency
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
CHAPTER 10
Integration of metabolism
1. 2. What happens mainly when a man runs 400 meters for 90 seconds?
A. Aerobic beta-oxidation
B. Lactate oxidation
C. Anaerobic metabolism from glycogen
D. Fatty acid from muscle
E. Liver produces ketone
A 50-year-old man slept for 8 hours then went for a jogging for 1 hour. Which of
the following is true?
A. B. C. D. E. Kidneys use ketone bodies as the main fuel
Muscle uses lactate as the main fuel
The heart uses ketone as the main fuel
The brain uses glucose as the main fuel
Cori cycle transport increased. Muscles and the liver are more metabolically
interlinked.
3. 4. 5. Why does glycogen in the liver have a larger mass-to-mass ratio than in muscle?
A. B. C. D. E. Glucose 1-phosphate stimulates glycogen synthesis in muscle.
Muscle hexokinase is less inhibited by glucose 6-phosphate.
Liver glucokinase is better stimulated by glucose.
Muscle hexokinase is better inhibited by glucose 6-phosphate.
Glycogen phosphorylase is inhibited by glucose 1-phosphate.
Adipose tissue relies on carbohydrate metabolism to generate triglycerides
because of the lack of which enzyme?
A. Phosphofructokinase – 1 (PFK – 1)
B. Glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase
C. Pyruvate kinase
D. Glycerol kinase
E. Glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase
What will happen when fatty acid oxidation occurs?
A. Citrate inhibits pyruvate dehydrogenase.
B. Acetyl-CoA inhibits pyruvate dehydrogenase.
C. Citrate activates pyruvate dehydrogenase.
D. Acetyl-CoA inhibits citrate synthase
E. Citrate inhibits acetyl CoA carboxylase
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
6. 7. 8. Which of the following effects occurs when the epinephrine level is high?
A. Decreased gluconeogenesis in the liver
B. Increased glycolysis in the heart
C. Decreased glycolysis in muscle
D. Increased ketogenesis by muscle
E. Increased uptake of glucose by adipose tissue
A protester hasn’t eaten any food in the past two weeks. Which is happening
currently in this person’s overall metabolism?
A. Kidney uses glutamine
B. Adipose tissue makes ketone bodies
C. Brain uses ketone bodies
D. High insulin/glucagon ratio
E. Muscle uses glucose
A 10-year-old boy normally looks healthy. He cannot perform any heavy exercise
since he easily develops fatigue, painful cramps, weakness, and sometimes
myoglobinuria. He has a better tolerance for aerobic exercise such as walking
and slow jogging. He never shows any symptoms of trembling, sweating, anxiety,
or fast heart-beating after the overnight sleep. Which of the following processes
is most likely a deficit in this patient?
A. Muscle beta-oxidation
B. Muscle ketogenesis
C. Muscle glycolysis
D. Liver gluconeogenesis
E. Adipose tissue lipolysis
CHAPTER 11
Calorimetry
1. What is the principle of direct calorimetry such as the Atwater and Benedict’s
calorimeter?
A. Detect heat production from body
B. Calculate energy metabolism from O2 usage
C. Calculate energy metabolism from nutrients eaten
D. Calculate energy from CO2 production
E. Calculate energy from the respiratory exchange ratio
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
2. 3. Which factor affects the respiratory exchange ratio of a 25-year-old woman the
most?
A. Thermic effect of food
B. Hormones, especially estrogen level
C. Physical activity
D. Ambient temperature
Which hormone contributes to the metabolic rate in the smallest amount?
A. Thyroid hormone
B. Growth hormone
C. Catecholamines
D. Sex hormones e.g. Testosterone
E. Leptin (satiety hormone)
CHAPTER 12
Vitamins I – Fat-soluble vitamins
1. 2. Warfarin is commonly used as an anticoagulant. What does this drug inhibit?
A. Vitamin K cycle
B. Vitamin K synthesis
C. Vitamin K absorption
D. Vitamin A synthesis
E. Vitamin A absorption
A patient with foamy patches in the eye was prescribed a medicine. The
symptoms then get better. What is the medication?
A. Tocopherol
B. Calciferol
C. Phylloquinone
D. Retinyl palmitate
E. Ascorbic acid
3. A patient with kidney failure is waiting for kidney transplantation after his
kidneys are surgically removed. What is not the consequence?
A. Lower calcium absorption from small intestine
B. Lower 24,25-dihydrovitamin D3 concentration
C. Lower active form of vitamin D3
D. Lower content of calbidin and TRPV
E. Lower activity of 1α-hydroxylase
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
CHAPTER 13
Vitamins II – Water-soluble vitamins
1. A neonatal baby is born with red lumps on lower back. Which vitamin may the
mother lack?
A. Thiamine
B. Niacin
C. Folate
D. Cobalamin
E. Riboflavin
2. 3. 4. A patient comes to the doctor complaining about having muscle cramps for an
abnormally long time. He is breathing faster than normal and his legs are
evidently swollen. He also said that he hasn’t been remembering things well and
have trouble balancing and walking. From further examination, he seems to have
abnormal eye movements. He is diagnosed with deficiency of a certain vitamin.
Which enzyme is affected in this patient?
A. ALA synthase
B. Alpha-ketoglutarate decarboxylase
C. Serine hydroxymethyltransferase
D. Dopamine beta-hydroxylase
E. Pyruvate dehydrogenase
A patient comes to the doctor with painful tongue and burning eyes. To confirm
that these symptoms are caused from a vitamin deficiency, which test should be
used?
A. Erythrocyte transketolase test
B. Glutathione reductase test
C. Tryptophan loading test
D. Histidine loading test
E. Schilling test
A patient who has been eating a lot of sushi lately comes to the doctor from
general weakness and paleness of skin. She has an organism like this picture in
her stool. Blood test reveals that she has macrocytic anemia. Which factors
should be elevated in her blood test?
A. Propionyl CoA
B. Cystathionine
C. Pyruvate
D. Lactate
E. Methylmalonic acid
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
5. 6. Mr. Somchai notes that he has paleness of skin and he can be fatigued a lot
easier than before. He has a lot of red spots over his skin and his gums are
inflamed. Which enzyme is affected if these symptoms are caused from a
vitamin deficiency?
A. Lysine hydroxylase
B. Glutamate decarboxylase
C. Transketolase
D. Acetyl CoA carboxylase
E. Pyruvate carboxylase
A patient has abnormal darkening and thickening of skin. He also complains
about itching because of skin rashes. He shows gastrointestinal symptoms in the
form of diarrhea. He also suffers from hallucinations and loss of memory. Which
nutrient might this patient lack?
A. Valine
B. Histidine
C. Phenylalanine
D. Methionine
E. Tryptophan
CHAPTER 14
Mineral metabolism
1. 2. Which condition is most commonly found in patients with end-stage renal
disease (ESRD)?
A. Hyponatremia
B. Hypokalemia
C. Hypophosphatemia
D. Hypomagnesemia
E. Hypocalcemia
Which of the following is correct regarding iron metabolism?
A. B. C. D. Iron content is mainly controlled via biliary excretion.
When iron is low in blood, TIBC also decreases.
Problems in the distal part of small intestine may cause iron malabsorption.
Ingestion of proton pump inhibitors decrease gastric acid secretion, which
lessens iron absorption.
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
3. 4. 5. 6. Which symptom or sign is NOT found in Wilson’s disease?
A. Eye defect
B. Muscle cramps
C. Liver dysfunction
D. Brain degeneration
E. K-f ring
Inadequate ingestion of which mineral may lead to skin rash and inflammation?
A. Zn
B. Fe
C. Se
D. Cu
E. Mg
Which of the following pairs should be eaten together to facilitate absorption?
A. Milk and Fe
B. Black coffee and Fe
C. Zinc sulfate and Cu
D. Vitamin D and Ca
E. Spinach and Ca
Which of the following is NOT the role of calcium?
A. Second messenger
B. Maintenance of osmolarity equilibrium
C. Maintenance of cell membrane permeability
D. Coagulation factor
E. Nerve impulse transmission
CHAPTER 15
Body temperature
1. A healthy 30-year-old man enters thermoneutral zone. Which mechanisms will
his body use first to control body temperature?
A. Vasoactive response
B. Non-shivering thermogenesis from brown adipose
C. Radiation
D. Shivering thermogenesis
E. Insensible rate of perspiration
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
2. Which factor isn’t used to indicate thermoneutral zone of a women?
A. Body composition
B. Humidity
C. Cloth
D. Sensitivity of changing temperature
E. Basal metabolic rate
3. A patient with body temperature of 38.3 degrees Celsius has been prescribed
with paracetamol. How can paracetamol relieve fever?
A. Inhibits interleukin release from immune cells
B. Cyclooxygenase inhibition
C. Prostaglandin inhibition at hypothalamus
D. Decreases cellular respiration rate
E. Changes distribution of water in the body
CHAPTER 16
ROS, antioxidants & oxidative stress
1. 2. 3. Which of the following reactions directly generates the most deleterious free
radical?
A. Dismutation
B. Fenton reaction
C. Conjugation
D. Hydroxylation
E. Methylation
Which free radical causes vasodilation?
A. Nitric oxide
B. Superoxide
C. Hydroxyl
D. Peroxide
E. Peroxynitrate
Which of the following does not lead to higher ROS production?
A. Infection
B. Reperfusion
C. Hard exercise
D. Food toxicant
E. High fruit & vegetable intake
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
CHAPTER 17
Metabolism of xenobiotics
1. 2. 3. Which of the following is not the effect of xenobiotics?
A. Pharmaceutical effect
B. Decrease excretion
C. Carcinogenic effect
D. Immunological response
E. Toxicity
Which of the following is correct about phase II of xenobiotics
biotransformation?
A. B. C. D. E. This occurs mainly at SER.
Most products are mercapturic acid conjugates.
Liver fibrosis will not have a significant effect on this process.
Mostly makes products more soluble.
None of this process involves entoxification.
Enzyme CYP3A4 is required in the biotransformation of acetaminophen
(paracetamol). Grapefruit juice inhibits CYP3A4 activity, whereas ginkgo
stimulates CYP3A4 activity. Which of the following correctly describes the
metabolism of acetaminophen?
A. Drinking grapefruit juice before taking paracetamol will benefit ultra-high
metabolizer.
B. C. D. NAPQI might be present at a higher level if he eats ginkgo with paracetamol.
All paracetamols will change to NAPQI if he eats gingko with paracetamol.
Grapefruit juice is an antidote the same as NAC.
CHAPTER 18
Food toxicology & food additives
1. Which of the following foods contains cyanogenic glycosides?
A. Cassava root
B. Cabbage
C. Potato
D. Broccoli
E. Red beans
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
2. 3. 4. 5. A patient is presented with rash, flushing and burning of the mouth and throat.
He ate scombroid fish. What type of toxin is in this fish meat?
A. Biogenic amines
B. Histamine
C. Tetrodotoxin
D. Saxitoxin
E. Glycoalkaloids
A patient with a suicidal attempt has an overstimulation of the parasympathetic
nervous system. The over-stimulation is resolved after atropine administration.
A condition in this patient is triggered by a chemical that has mechanisms of
action similar to that of which of the following?
A. Amanitin
B. DDT
C. Primaquine
D. Aflatoxin
E. Organophosphate
Patients have been sent to the hospital in Mae Sot district, Tak province
following eating home-canned bamboo shoots. Of six cases hospitalized, four
needed mechanical ventilation. All cases experienced neurological features.
Which of the following proteins in these patients was most likely to be cleaved?
A. Acetylcholineesterase
B. G-protein
C. SNARE protein
D. Clathrin
E. Synaptotagmin
A 25-year-old immigrant is present with numbness and tingling at the lips and
mouth 1 hour after eating puffer fish. Which toxin has a similar action?
A. Amanitin
B. Saxitoxin
C. Histamine
D. Carbamate
E. Plant lectin
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
6. A patient comes with an oxalate stone in the urinary bladder. Which of the
following food additives should he not consume?
A. Stevia
B. Xylitol
C. Sucralose
D. Aspartame
E. Saccharin
CHAPTER 19
Alcohol metabolism
1. Which of the following situations causes flushing when alcohol is taken?
A. B. C. D. E. High ADH and low ALDH
Low ADH and low ALDH
High ADH and high ALDH
High CYP2E1 and low ALDH
Low CYP2E1 and high ALDH
2. Which of the following enzymes manage alcohol and drug interaction?
A. ADH
B. ALDH
C. Catalase
D. GSH reductase
E. NADPH oxidase
3. Which method does alcoholic patients with 4 years of excessive alcohol intake
eliminate alcohol the most?
A. Using ADH in cytosol
B. Using ADH in microsome
C. CYP2E1 in cytosol
D. CYP2E1 in microsome
E. Catalase in peroxisome
4. Which of the following is not related to liver cancer formation in alcoholism?
A. Acetaldehyde accumulation
B. Microbiota compartment changes leading to changes in gut permeability
C. Gene susceptibility
D. Increased ratio of NADH/NAD+ leading to increased fatty acid oxidation
E. Formation of reactive oxygen species
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
5. What is the most dangerous metabolite in alcohol metabolism?
A. Acetone
B. Acetaldehyde
C. Acetyl CoA
D. Beta-hydroxybutyrate
E. Acetic acid
CHAPTER 20
LAB OGTT
1. A patient has fasting plasma glucose of 110 mg/dl and OGTT test plasma
glucose of 120 mg/dl. Please interpret the results of the blood sugar level.
A. Normal
B. Impaired fasting glucose
C. Impaired glucose tolerance
D. Impaired fasting glucose and impaired glucose tolerance
E. Diabetes
2. Which substance will not cause positive results in O-toluidine test?
A. Galactose
B. Deoxyribose
C. Lactose
D. Glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate
E. Fructose
3. What is the enzyme for detecting glucose in the glucose sensor?
A. Glycosyl peroxidase
B. Glucose dehydrogenase
C. Glucose monooxygenase
D. Glucose oxidase
E. Glucose transporter
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
CHAPTER 21
LAB Calorimetry & Body Temperature
1. 2. A person in room temperature puts one of his legs to a 15oC water bath. Which
result is NOT expected?
A. Piloerection
B. Trunk shivering
C. Vasodilation of the leg in water bath and vasoconstriction of the other leg
D. Vasoconstriction in both legs
E. Hypothermia (Lower core temperature)
Which factor is not used to calculate metabolic rate from the portable
automated gas analysis system, and also comparing the results to the calculated
normal resting metabolic rate?
A. Age, sex, weight and ethnicity
B. Urine nitrogen
C. Body temperature
D. Rate of oxygen usage
E. Rate of CO2 release
3. Which mechanism does the Benedict-Roth spirometer use to
measure metabolic rate?
A. B. C. D. Volume of CO2 produced and O2 consumed in a day
Volume of CO2 produced and O2 consumed in an amount of time
Volume of O2 consumed in a day
Volume of O2 consumed in an amount of time
CHAPTER 22
LAB Food additives determination
1. Food containing bleaching agents should not be taken by patients with what?
A. Asthma
B. Urolithiasis
C. Cholecystitis
D. Hepatitis
E. Tuberculosis
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
2. MJPK screening kit is developed for pesticide detection, using the principle of
enzyme inhibition. Which enzyme is inhibited by pesticide in this kit?
A. Decarboxylase
B. Acetylcholinesterase
C. Monooxygenase
D. NADPH oxidase
E. Xanthine oxidase
3. IARC defines salami, sausage as carcinogenic type1 . Which test is used to mark
the presence of the carcinogen?
A. Hexacyanoferrate
B. Phenylhydrazine
C. Ethyl acetate
D. Brucine
E. Sulfate
CHAPTER 23
Problem solving on integration of metabolism
1. 2. A patient comes to the doctor with irritability, seizures and peripheral
neuropathy. Blood test reveals hypochromic microcytic anemia. Past history
taking reveals isoniazid intake for treating tuberculosis. The patient is lacking in
a certain vitamin. Which is true in patients with this vitamin deficiency?
A. Increase in orotate
B. Increase in formiminoglutamate
C. Increase in homocysteine
D. Decrease in globin synthesis
E. Decrease in niacytin
Which reaction does not occur in ketogenic diet?
A. Gluconeogenesis
B. Lipolysis
C. Ketogenesis
D. Glycogenesis
E. Ketolysis
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
3. 4. 5. A physically active individual, engaged in regular exercise, presented at the
hospital with extensive desquamation. Upon examination, a deficiency in
Vitamin B7 is identified in this patient. What could be a plausible conclusion
based on these findings?
A. He will recover fast if treated by PLP.
B. He may suffer from hyperammonemia.
C. He is suspected of having a genetic mutant of the enzyme responsible for this
reaction: propionyl-CoA → methylmalonyl-CoA.
D. The dietary supplement he took was an omelet.
A 70-year-old patient is admitted due to severe bone fractures. She has a history
of smoking a box of cigarettes every day for 45 years. X-ray results reveal signs
of osteoporosis. Which of the following forms of vitamin D should be used for the
diagnosis of vitamin D deficiency?
A. Ergocalciferol
B. 1-alpha-hydroxyvitamin D
C. 25-hydroxyvitamin D
D. 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D
E. 24,25-dihydroxyvitamin D
From the diagram regarding drug metabolism: what is A, B and C, respectively?
A B C Drug Oxidized drug Detoxified drug Excretion
  
A. CYP2E1, oxidation, hydrophilic
B. CYP450, reduction, hydrophobic
C. CYP2E1, reduction, hydrophobic
D. CYP450, glucuronation, hydrophobic
E. CYP450, sulfate conjugate, hydrophilic
END OF THE EXAM PAPER
ขอใหนอง ๆ โชคดีในการสอบใหญรอบแรกของนอง ๆ นะฮะ
เขาใจวามันยาก หนักและเหนื่อยมาก แตเชื่อวาจะผานมันไปไดนะ ^^
 อานตรง เดาถูก เก็ท E กันทุกคนจา 
สาธุๆๆๆๆๆ
