--- ##midterm test past paper ---
ACetaldehyde81
3050108 Cell Biology and Medical Biochemistry
Part II: Metabolism
Peer Support 81
pg. 1
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Preface and Acknowledgement
ฝ"ายวิชาการชั้นป.ที่ 1 ป.การศึกษา 2568 ได=จัดทําเอกสารรวบรวมข=อสอบกลางภาค (AC81) ในรายวิชา
3050108 Cell Biology and Medical Biochemistry จากความรbวมมือของเพื่อน ๆ MDCU81 พร=อมทั้งแตbง
เติมปรับแก=ไขโจทยkบางข=อที่ขาดหายไป เพื่อเปmนประโยชนkให=กับเพื่อน ๆ และรุbนน=องป.ถัด ๆ ไปในการทบทวน
เนื้อหาประเด็นสําคัญทางชีววิทยาระดับเซลลkและชีวเคมีเพื่อพัฒนาตนเองและแก=ไขข=อบกพรbองของตนเองใน
เนื้อหารายวิชานี้ รวมถึงเปmนประโยชนkในการตbอยอดความรู=ไปใช=ใน block ถัด ๆ ไปและใช=ประยุกตkในการเรียน
ตbอทางแพทยkและการวิจัยตbอไป
เอกสารนี้มีจุดประสงคkเปmนเพียงแคbตัวชbวยในการทบทวนสำหรับการสอบเทbานั้น ทางฝ"ายวิชาการไมb
แนะนําให=ใช=เอกสารนี้เพียงอยbางเดียวในการทบทวนเพื่อใช=ในการสอบวัดผล และแนะนําให=ทบทวนเนื้อหาที่
อาจารยkสอนผbานระบบ E-learning ควบคูbไปด=วย หรือสามารถทบทวนเนื้อหาเพิ่มเติมจากทรัพยากรใน
MDCU81 Academic Page เพื่อการเตรียมตัวสอบที่ครบถ=วนและมีประสิทธิภาพสูงสุด
ทางฝ"ายวิชาการหวังวbาเอกสารฉบับนี้จะทำให=เพื่อน ๆ และน=อง ๆ ทุกคนที่เข=ามาใช=เอกสารฉบับนี้ได=
ทบทวนและทำความเข=าใจประเด็นที่สําคัญทางชีววิทยาระดับเซลลk (Cell Biology) และชีวเคมี
(Biochemistry) เพื่อประโยชนkสำหรับการสอบและการนำไปตbอยอดในอนาคตไมbมากก็น=อย
สุดท=ายนี้ ฝ"ายวิชาการชั้นป.ที่ 1 ป.การศึกษา 2568 ขอเปmนกำลังใจให=เพื่อน ๆ และน=อง ๆ ทุกคนในการ
สอบ และขอให=ทุกคนได=คะแนนที่สมปรารถนาและมีความสุขในการเรียนแพทยkไปตลอด 6 ป.นี้
ในนามของฝ"ายวิชาการชั้นป.ที่ 1 ป.การศึกษา 2568
ขอขอบพระคุณเพื่อน ๆ ที่สนับสนุนและคอยเปmนกำลังใจให=ทีม PS81 เสมอมา
หากมีข=อผิดพลาดใด ๆ ในเอกสารฉบับนี้ก็ขออภัยมา ณ ที่นี้
นายกานตk กิตติรัตนkพัฒนา
หัวหน=าฝ"ายวิชาการชั้นป.ที่ 1 ป.การศึกษา 2568
นายปภาวิน วาสนาสbงชูสกุล
นายพชร ตั้งตรงจิตร
ประธานฝ"ายวิชาการ 81 รายวิชา 3050108
Cell Biology and Medical Biochemistry
pg. 2
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Table of Specification
หัวข%อ จำนวนข%อ pg.
Introduction to metabolism 2 4
Carbohydrate Metabolism 6 5
Amino acid metabolism 6 7
Nucleotide metabolism 3 9
Lipid Metabolism 8 10
Alcohol Metabolism 3 13
Mineral Metabolism 3 14
Vitamins I (Water-soluble) 4 15
Vitamins II (fat-soluble) 2 17
Selected clinical cases in tissue and organ metabolism 4 18
Case Discussion III-IV 2 19
pg. 3
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Chapter I
Introduction to metabolism
อ.ดร.พรชัย แก,วทรัพย/ศักดิ์
1. Thermodynamically, what is the mechanism of enzymes when added to reactions?
A. They decrease the ΔH of the reaction.
B. They decrease the ΔG of the reaction.
C. They decrease the ΔS of the reaction.
D. They do not change the activation energy
E. They do not change the ΔS of the reaction.
2. A patient is exposed to an uncoupling agent. Which of the following is the
consequence?
A. Inhibition of proton gradient
(ไมbมีข=อมูลตัวเลือกอื่น)
pg. 4
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Chapter II
Carbohydrate Metabolism
ศ.ดร.สัญชัย พยุงภร
1. A patient with type II diabetes mellitus comes in for evaluation. The physician wants
to detect glucose level 2-3 months prior. What should be tested?
A. Serum glucose
B. Serum albumin
C. Glycated albumin
D. Hemoglobin A1c
E. Fasting blood glucose
2. A patient has a history of recurrent respiratory tract infection since infancy. Lab
investigations show the impairment of phagocytic respiratory burst. Which enzyme is
most likely defected?
A. Myeloperoxidase
B. NADPH oxidase
C. Glucose 6-phosphate dehydrogenase
D. Glucose 6-phosphatase
E. Superoxide dismutase
3. Scientists are conducting an experiment on gluconeogenesis. When biotin is
removed, which substance is decreased?
A. Succinate
B. Phosphoenolpyruvate
C. Malate
D. Oxaloacetate
E. Pyruvate
pg. 5
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
4. An infant patient was admitted to the hospital, presented with diarrhea after
breastfeeding. She also has hypergalactosemia, galacturia, and mild hepatomegaly.
What enzyme is likely impaired in this patient?
A. Galactose 1-phosphate uridyltransferase
B. Aldolase B
C. Fructokinase
D. Glucose 6-phosphatase
E. Fructose 1,6-bisphosphatase
5. Which of the following enzymes are regulated by insulin and glucagon respectively?
A. Phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase, Pyruvate kinase
B. Phosphofructokinase-1, Fructose 1,6-bisphosphatase
C. Hexokinase, Glucose 6-phosphatase
D. Glucokinase, Pyruvate carboxylase
E. Fructose 2,6-bisphosphatase, Phosphofructokinase-2
6. A patient is presented with lactic acidosis after consuming excessive amounts of
fructose. How can fructose cause this symptom?
A. Bypassing the key regulatory step of glycolysis
B. Inhibiting the regulatory enzyme of glycolysis
(ไมbมีข=อมูลตัวเลือกอื่น)
pg. 6
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Chapter III
Amino acid metabolism
อ.ดร.พรชัย แก,วทรัพย/ศักดิ์
1. Which amino acid cannot be metabolized into succinyl CoA?
A. Valine
B. Methionine
C. Isoleucine
D. Leucine
E. Threonine
2. A patient is presented with mild hyperammonemia and plasma arginine
accumulation. What enzyme is defected?
A. Arginase
B. N-acetylglutamate synthase
C. Ornithine transcarbamoylase
D. Argininosuccinate lyase
E. Carbamoyl phosphate synthetase II
3. A patient has symptoms resembling pellagra. Lab tests show that an amino acid
cannot be absorbed in the intestine. Which amino acid is it?
A. Threonine
B. Tyrosine
C. Tryptophan
D. Leucine
E. Methionine
pg. 7
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
4. A patient is presented with homocysteinemia and decreased enzymatic activity of
cystathionine β-synthase. What vitamin is most likely involved in this pathology?
A. B2
B. B3
C. B6
D. B9
E. B12
5. A 5-year-old patient has an absence of melanin pigment in the skin and hair but is
otherwise healthy. What enzyme is likely impaired?
A. Phenylalanine hydroxylase
B. Tyrosinase
C. Homogentisate 1,2-dioxygenase
D. DOPAchrome tautomerase
E. Tyrosine aminotransferase
α-keto acid dehydrogenase
6. A kid is presented with acidosis and sweet odor in urine. What enzyme is defected?
A. Methionine adenosyl transferase
B. Branched-chain C. Phenylalanine hydroxylase
D. Homogentisate 1,2-dioxygenase
E. Branched-chain α-keto acid aminotransferase
pg. 8
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Chapter IV
Nucleotide metabolism
ผศ.ดร.ธนัญญา ทองตัน
1. Regarding allopurinol, what is NOT true?
A. Increase salvage pathway of purine
B. Increase of PRPP
C. Increase of hypoxanthine
D. Decrease of xanthine
E. Decrease of de novo purine synthesis
2. What is used to measure DNA turnover?
A. Uric acid
B. β-alanine
C. β-aminoisobutyrate
D. NH4
+
E. CO2
3. What reaction is catalyzed by rNDP reductase?
A. dUMP to dTMP
B. ADP to dADP
C. GDP to GTP
D. XMP to GTP
E. AMP to IMP
pg. 9
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Chapter V
Lipid Metabolism
รศ.ดร.ชาลิสา หลุยเจริญ ชีพสุนทร
1. Blood tests show low plasma carnitine and elevated serum free fatty acid. What is
most likely to be defected?
A. Carnitine
B. CAT I
C. SCOT
D. MTP
E. ACC
2. A patient comes to the hospital for a follow-up examination. She has a 40-year-old
father who had an incidence of myocardial infarction. Blood tests show turbid plasma.
Lipid profiles show triglycerides of 250 mg/dL, total cholesterol of 300 mg/dL, and HDL
of 40 mg/dL. Which of the following is true about this patient?
A. Apo B deficiency
B. Apo C deficiency
C. LCAT deficiency
D. LPL deficiency
E. Normal LDL levels
pg. 10
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
3. A 50-year-old patient with a history of myocardial infarction is currently receiving
aspirin therapy. The patient presents with symptoms of asthma. What is the most
likely underlying mechanism for these respiratory symptoms observed in this case?
A. Inhibit COX and arachidonic acid is then diverted to leukotriene pathway
B. Inhibit COX and increased prostacyclin production leads to airway hyperreactivity
C. Inhibit LOX and decreased leukotriene pathway
D. Inhibit LOX and increased synthesis of thromboxane pathway
E. Inhibit PLA2 and decreased synthesis of eicosanoids
4. Dysfunction of which structure causes xanthoma at Achilles tendon?
A. LDL receptor
B. LPL
C. MTP
D. Apo C-II
E. CPT-I
5. A patient is diagnosed with SCOT deficiency. What is NOT a symptom of this
patient?
A. Persistent ketoacidosis
B. Normal glucose levels between episodes
C. Episodes of lethargy
(ไมbมีข=อมูลตัวเลือกอื่น)
pg. 11
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
6. A patient is treated with statins and bile acid sequestrants. What is the consequence
of this treatment?
A. ACAT is fully active after treatment
B. LDL receptor increases after treatment
C. Bile acid sequestrant directly inhibits cholesterol 7-alpha hydroxylase.
(ไมbมีข=อมูลตัวเลือกอื่น)
7. A patient is presented to the out-patient department. Lab investigations showed
hyperglycerolemia and glyceroluria. Which of the following is true?
A. Phosphorylation of glycerol in adipose tissue
B. Defect in glycerol kinase
C. Glycerol dehydrogenase isn’t involved.
(ไมbมีข=อมูลตัวเลือกอื่น)
8. (ไมbมีข=อมูล)
pg. 12
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Chapter VI
Alcohol Metabolism
ผศ.ดร.ณัฐธยาน/ ชDวยเพ็ญ
1. A 30-year-old East Asian man experiences facial flushing after moderate alcohol
intake. Which enzyme is likely to be deficient?
A. Alcohol dehydrogenase
B. Aldehyde dehydrogenase
C. Cytochrome P450 2E1
D. Glucose 6-phosphate dehydrogenase
E. Catalase
2. What is the primary enzyme used to metabolize ethanol in patients with chronic
alcoholism?
A. CYP2E1
B. ADH
C. ALDH
D. Catalase
E. G6PD
3. What is the toxic substance that comes from the ingestion of methanol?
A. Formaldehyde
B. Acetaldehyde
C. Acetate
D. Malonate
E. Lactate
pg. 13
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Chapter VII
Mineral Metabolism
ผศ.ดร.ณัฐธยาน/ ชDวยเพ็ญ
1. What is the mechanism of high sodium intake that leads to hypertension?
A. Extracellular fluid retention leading to increased cardiac output
B. Increase renin secretion from juxtaglomerular cell
(ไมbมีข=อมูลตัวเลือกอื่น)
2. Which of the following is the etiology of hereditary hemochromatosis?
A. Hepcidin deficiency leading to increased iron plasma intake
B. Excess ferritin degradation in macrophages
(ไมbมีข=อมูลตัวเลือกอื่น)
3. In Wilson disease, which of the following process of ATP7B is inhibited?
A. Retrograde transport from endosome to Golgi
B. Anterograde transport from Golgi to cell membrane
(ไมbมีข=อมูลตัวเลือกอื่น)
pg. 14
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Chapter VIII
Vitamins I (Water-soluble)
ศ.ดร.นพ.สิทธิศักดิ์ หรรษาเวก
1. A blood test is performed on a patient. Hypersegmented leukocytes are found and
mean corpuscular volume is 115 fL. High levels of plasma homocysteine and
methylmalonic acid are also found. What is the LEAST likely cause in this patient?
A. Infection of Diphyllobothrium latum
B. Meat eater
C. Bacterial overgrowth
D. Gastric bypass surgery
E. Pancreatitis
2. A patient presents with burning eyes, sore tongue and cracked lips. What test is the
most appropriate for this patient?
A. Erythrocyte transketolase test
B. Erythrocyte glutathione reductase test
C. Tryptophan loading test
D. Histidine loading test
E. Schilling test
pg. 15
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
3. A patient undergoes treatment and takes a medication for Mycobacterium
tuberculosis. She returns to the hospital with a burning foot sensation. What should be
supplemented for this patient?
A. Tocopherol
B. Riboflavin
C. Pyridoxine
D. Cobalamin
E. Thiamine
4. An 80-year-old woman comes into the hospital with easy bruising. She has a history
of chronic alcohol use, IV drug use, 20-pack-years of smoking. She also has swollen
gum, petechiae of the hair, and 2 non-healing sacral wounds. What vitamin is most
likely to be deficient?
A. Ascorbic acid
B. Thiamine
C. Niacin
D. Riboflavin
E. Folic acid
pg. 16
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Chapter IX
Vitamins II (Fat-soluble)
ผศ.ดร.ชัยบุตร อริยะเชษฐ
1. Which substance is low in patients with RPE65 defect compared to a normal person?
A. Cis retinal
B. Trans retinal
C. Retinol
D. Retinoic acid
E. Retinyl palmitate
2. A patient undergoes a total nephrectomy due to renal cell carcinoma. He later
develops symptoms such as bowing of the legs. What happened?
A. Calcitriol can’t be activated.
(ไมbมีข=อมูลตัวเลือกอื่น)
pg. 17
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Chapter X
Selected clinical cases in tissue and organ
metabolism
ศ.ดร.นพ.สิทธิศักดิ์ หรรษาเวก
1. A patient has elevated very-long-chain fatty acid levels. Electron microscopy imaging
found the dysfunction of an organelle. Which of the following is also produced by this
organelle?
A. Oxidative phosphorylase
B. Hydroxylase
C. Glucocerebrosidase
D. Bile acids
E. Myeloperoxidase
2. (ไมbมีข=อมูล)
3. (ไมbมีข=อมูล)
4. (ไมbมีข=อมูล)
pg. 18
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Chapter XI
Case Discussion III-IV
คณาจารย/
1. (Case 3 – Glycogen Storage Disease)
A 1-year-old boy is diagnosed with Von Gierke disease. He is presented with
hyperuricemia. This symptom can be explained with which pathway?
A. Pentose phosphate pathway
B. Gluconeogenesis
C. Urea cycle
D. TCA cycle
E. Glycolysis
2. (Case 4 – Ornithine transcarbamoylase deficiency and Vitamin B12 deficiency)
(ไมbมีข=อมูล)
pg. 19
