--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Academic 75
3000109
FUND CELL MOL BIO MID-TERM 75
ข้อสอบจริงเป็นข้อสอบแบบ MCQs จำนวน 100 ข้อ เวลาสอบทั้งสิ้น 120 นาที
1. Which one is composed of microfilaments?
A. cilia
B. flagellum
C. basal body
D. centriole
E. stereocilia
2. A student measures the absorbance of standard Potassium Permanganate solution 10 times (0.5mM) and
calculates mean concentration and %CV which is 0.49mM and 12% , respectively. Which techniques this
student uses?
A. Good technique
B. Random Error
C. Systemic Error
D. Accurate and Precise
E. Not Accurate but Precise
3. A 50-year-old man presents with left toe swells and in pain. He said he had too many beers last night. On
examination, his big right toe is swollen, warm, red and very painful. Which of the following is most likely to
cause the symptoms?
A. sphingomyelin
B. leukotriene
C. cholesterol
D.
E.
4. Which of the following is correct?
A. B. C. D. E. Biomarker of oxidative stress is serum malonaldehyde.
Ganglioside contains sphingosine and cholesterol backbones.
Hydrogenated vegetable oil stays liquid at room temperature.
Fatty acids are the most abundant energy source for vertebrates.
Cis-double bonds form kinks in fatty acid tail, allowing them to pack tight together.
1
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
5. 6. 7. 8. 9. Academic 75
Which one of the following does not have a reducing property?
A. lactose
B. maltose
C. fructose
D. sucrose
E. glucose
Which of the following are proteins with similar function?
A. Casein, Keratin
B. Thrombin, Fibrin
C. Actin, Vasopressin
D. Immunoglobulin, Collagen
E. Platelet-derived growth factor, Insulin
A researcher studies a reaction and finds that the reaction releases Pi from an X-substance. A calculated
rG is equal to 7 kcal/mol. Which of the following is LEAST likely correct?
A. It is an exergonic reaction.
B. Basically, it is irreversible.
C. Basically, it is spontaneous.
D. X-substance is a high energy phosphate compound.
E. ปฏิกิริยาสามารถผลักดันให้เกิดการสร้าง ATP โดยใช้ ADP และ Pi ได้
Which is not a health benefit of sorbitol?
A. Laxative
B. Energy intake control
C. Dental caries prevention
D. Diabetes mellitus treatment
E. Prebiotics for colonic bacteria
Which of the following is a heteroglycan?
A. amylose
B. cellulose
C. glycogen
D. amylopectin
E. peptidoglycan
2
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Academic 75
10. When cell or tissue absorbs uncoupling agents, which of the following most likely occurred immediately?
A. Increasing P:O ratio
B. Decreasing O2 consumption
C. Increasing cellular temperature
D. No electron flow in electron transport chain
E. Increasing proton gradient across mitochondrial inner membrane
11. Protease has a binding pocket which binds to lysine and arginine. Which amino acid does the binding
iiipocket have?
A. alanine
B. tyrosine
C. histamine
D. glutamine
E. asparagine
12. Which one does not have N-glycosidic linkage?
A. DNA
B. RNA
C. Hyaluronan
D. Glycoprotein
E. .
i
13. It is well accepted that hemolysis interferes the accuracy of blood chemistry measurement. Measurement
ffffffffof which ion most likely to be falsely in hemolytic sample?
A. Proton
B. Sodium
C. Calcium
D. Chloride
E. Potassium
14. DNA is being treated with mutagen and the melting temperature graph is shifted to the left. Which can be
iiithe possible cause for this?
A. Increase in methylation
B. Increase in double strand break
C. Base substitution from G to A
D. Increase in melting temperature
E. Change from purine to pyrimidine
3
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Academic 75
15. Proteins can form amyloid fibrils which is the cause of some neurodegenerative diseases. What is the origin
iicause of formation of amyloid fibrils?
A. Protein denaturation
B. Protein misfolding
C. Lack of protein
D. Post-translational modification
E. Mutation of single nucleotide
16. Pepsin จะทำงานได้ดีขึ้นเมื่อใส่สารในข้อใด?
A. HCl
B. HCO3
-
C. NaOH
D. NaCl
E. Pepstatin
17. Sphingomyelin contains which of the following component?
A. glycerol, phosphoric acid, 2 fatty acids, choline
B. sphingosine, phosphoric acid, 1 fatty acid, choline
C. sphingosine, phosphoric acid, 2 fatty acids
D. glycerol, phosphoric acids, 2 fatty acids
E.
18. Which transitional metal is essential to the method for detecting peptide bond?
A. Cobalt
B. Nickel
C. Copper
D. Ferrous
E. Manganese
19. Which of the following is correct about Km?
A. The concentration of substrate when v = vmax
B. The half of concentration of the substrate at vmax
C. The concentration of substrate which half of enzyme is bonded
D. The point of the graph at which half of substrate is used up
E. The kinetic value of enzyme at which relates to substrate-binding affinity
4
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Academic 75
i
20. Which process or reaction turns monosaccharide derivatives to N-acetylneuraminic acid (NANA)?
A. Oxidation
B. Amination
C. Reduction
D. Phosphorylation
E. Glycosidic linkage
21. Which amino acid are mostly found in membrane G coupler receptors?
A. Acid amino acid
B. Basic amino acid
C. Non-polar amino acid
D. Aromatic amino acid
E. Uncharged amino acid
22. To separate protein B out, which of these processes should be used?
A : 860 kDa , +3 charged
B : 500 kDa ,
-3 charged
C : 480 kDa , +3 charged
A. Gas liquid chromatography
B. Agarose gel electrophoresis
C. Gel filtration chromatography
D. Ion exchange chromatography
E. Affinity chromatography
23. Which one is not biological function of protein?
A. Cell movement
B. Regulation of metabolism
C. Reaction of catalyst
D. Primary source of energy
E. Defense against bacteria
24. Ras is a key protein in regulation of cell proliferation. In normal circumstance, after Ras is synthesized. It
will bind to the cell membrane. A drug act by preventing Ras from moving from cytoplasm and binding to
cell membrane. If a scientist wants to see if the drug works properly, what microscope should be used?
A. SEM
B. TEM
C. DIC
D. Phase contrast
E. Fluorescence microscope
5
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Academic 75
25. A restriction enzyme cuts DNA into three strands
Gel electrophoresis is used to determine the size of these DNA strands. What would the result must be ?
26. Which of the following is ATP synthesize reaction by substrate level phosphorylation?
A. ADP + Pi —> ATP ; ATP Synthase
B. Phosphoenolpyruvate + ADP —> Pyruvate + ATP
C. ADP + GTP —> GDP + ATP
D. ADP + ADP —> ATP + AMP
E. …
27. What is the name of body circled in the picture?
A. Peroxisome
B. Fat Droplet
C. Secretory Granule
D. SER
6
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
28. 29. 30. 31. Academic 75
E. Lysosome
What is the substance that makes the sigmoid curve of an allosteric enzyme activity shown more S curve
called?
A. Inducer
B. Inhibitor
C. Cofactor
D. Activator
E. Repressor
What ___ detoxification conjugated mechanism?
A. Galactitol
B. Glucosamine
C. Glucuronic acid
D. Mannose-6-phosphate
E. Methyl-alpha-G-glucoside
What type of microscope these photos have been taken from?
A. Inducer
B. Inhibitor
C. Cofactor
D. Activator
E. Repressor
Which molecule is least likely to be positive for Xanthoproteic test?
A. LDL
B. Collagen
C. Chromatin
D. Glutathione
E. Hemoglobin
7
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Academic 75
32. Which is not involved in Folin-Ciocalteu assay?
A. Tyrosine
B. Calcium ion
C. Sodium Hydroxide
D. Phosphotungstic acid
E. Phosphomolybdic acid
33. Which is the key characteristic of cell apoptosis but not in necrosis?
A. Cell Swelling
B. Cell disintegrate
C. DNA fragmentation
D. Membrane breakdown
E. Injury of cell membrane
34. Which amino acid is most likely to be associated with Transmembrane domain of G protein-coupled
reaction?
A. Acidic amino acid
B. Basic amino acid
C. Aromatic amino acid
D. Nonpolar amino acid
E. Uncharged polar amino acid
35. Which organelle is mostly associated with macrophage?
A. Lysosome
B. Mitochondria
C. Peroxisome
D. RER
E. SER
36. Biogenesis of which organelle is associated with RER?
A. Lysosome
B. Mitochondria
C. Peroxisome
D. SER
E. Nuclear envelope
8
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
37. 38. 39. 40. 41. Academic 75
Which is not an essential component for SEM?
A. Electron gun
B. Diamond Knife
C. Condenser
D. Vacuum Pump
E. Gold nanoparticles
Which of the following is used in a chemical method for cell lysis?
A. Triton-X
B. Hypotonic solution
C. Blender
D. Tissue grinder
E. Protease
From thermodynamic laws, which sentences is correct?
A. The reaction that has a positive ΔG0’ can’t be occur in the reverse direction.
B. The reaction that has a negative ΔG0’ can’t be occur in the reverse direction.
C. The reaction that has a negative ΔH0 and positive ΔS0 values is the spontaneous reaction.
D. The reaction that has a positive ΔH0 and negative ΔS0 values is the non-spontaneous reaction.
E. The reaction that has a negative ΔH0 and negative ΔS0 values is the non-spontaneous reaction.
Which of the following is incorrect about protein?
A. Not all proteins have quaternary structure.
B. Side group of amino acid is a part of peptide bond planar.
C. A common type of protein domain can be found in different proteins.
D. Secondary structure of protein cannot tell whether the protein is water-soluble or not.
E. Hydrophobic interaction is considered in tertiary structure of protein.
Which of the following chemical bond is H-bond?
A. A
B. B
C. C
D. D
E. E
9
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
42. 43. 44. 45. 46. Academic 75
Which is incorrect about human proteome?
A. It consists of all proteins human produced.
B. Selenoproteins are excluded from human proteome.
C. Number of proteins can be increased in human proteome.
D. ….
E. Human genome can help predict human proteome.
Which of the following glycosidic linkages is hydrolyzed by amylase enzyme?
A. α(1,2)
B. α(1,4)
C. α(1,6)
D. β(1,2)
E. β(1,4)
Which one is the glycosidic bond of starch?
A. α(1,2)
B. α(1,4)
C. α(1,6)
D. β(1,2)
E. β(1,4)
Which amino acid residue of glycoprotein are mostly attached to carbohydrate moiety?
A. Phe Val Glu
B. Arg Tys Gln
C. Asn Ser Thr
D. Gly Ala Asp
E. Thr Asp Cys
Carbonic anhydrase (CA) is an enzyme that catalyzes the following reversible reaction:
H2CO3 <-> H2O + CO2
In an experiment, same amount of CO2 and H2CO3 solution are put into two tightly closed test tubes
labeled as 1 and 2. All conditions are the same, except enzyme CA is added only into tube 2. The reactions
are let to reach the equilibrium. Then, CA enzyme is added to tube 1 in a closed system. Which one is
the correct comparison between the 2 tubes?
A. Equal amount of H2CO3 in both tubes
B. No CO2 in test tube 1
C. No H2CO3 in test tube 1
D. Tube 1 contains some but less CO2
E. Tube 1 contains some but less H2CO3
10
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
47. 48. 49. 50. Academic 75
Which fatty acid has the highest melting point?
A. Dodecanoic acid
B. Octadecanoic acid
C. Octadecenoic acid
D. Octadecadienoic acid
E. Octadecatrienoic acid
The result of Lineweaver-Burk plot for an enzyme kinetic study shows the linear line with
y = 0.400x + 0.500. What is the Vmax of this enzyme?
A. 0.4
B. 0.8
C. 2.0
D. 2.5
E. 5.0
Which compound consists of sulfhydryl and amino group?
A. ATP
B. Threonine
C. Glutathione
D. Cholesterol ester
E. Adenosine
Which of these statements is true?
A. Asp is acidic.
B. Glu is basic.
C. Asp is more acidic than basic.
D. Glu is more acidic than basic.
E. Glu is more basic than acidic.
11
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
51. 52. 53. Academic 75
Which of the following reagents is used to separate protein according to weight and subunits?
A. SDS, beta-mercaptoethanol
B. acrylamide, bis-acrylamide
C. deoxycholate, triton-X
D. chloroform, methanol
E. potassium thiocyanate
From the membrane’s selective permeable properties, which of the following molecule is likely to be the
hardest molecule passing the membrane?
A. Na+
B. CO2
C. NH3
D. H2O
E. Cholesterol
From the table, which of these is correct?
v
[S]
Control A B
0 0.0 0.0 0.0
1 10.0 7.5 1.0
2 13.0 10.0 2.7
4 18.0 14.0 5.4
6 21.0 16.9 8.0
8 22.5 19.0 10.5
10 23.7 21.6 12.6
15 24.0 23.0 17.0
20 24.0 23.7 20.0
25 24.0 24.0 22.4
30 24.0 24.0 24.0
A. A = competitive, B = competitive
B. A = non-competitive, B = non-competitive
C. A = competitive, B = non-competitive
D. A = non-competitive, B = competitive
E. A = non-competitive, B = uncompetitive
12
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Academic 75
54. Which of the following is used for Agarose gel electrophoresis?
A.
B.
C.
D.
E.
13
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
55. 56. 57. 58. 59. Academic 75
Which of the following is not found in electron transport chain in mitochondria?
A. NADH
B. FADH2
C. Ubiquitin
D. Coenzyme Q10
E. Cytochrome C
What property is not belong to water?
A. Increasing fluidity in cell membrane
B. Dipole-Dipole
C. Separating hydrophobic from hydrophilic
D. Create H-bond with high-EN elements (such as N, O, F)
E. Form aqueous environment and hydrolysis
Ligase enzyme contains a lysine residue which is important for its DNA binding ability. A mutation is found
to convert lysine into five different amino acids. Which mutated amino acid is predicted to be most harmful
to the enzyme activity?
A. Glycine
B. Histidine
C. Arginine
D. Cysteine
E. Aspartate
Which derivative of these monosaccharides accumulates in the eye lens and cause cataract?
A. Fucose
B. Sorbitol
C. Fructose
D. Glucosamine
E. Glucuronic acid
Six molecules of NADH are produced in cytosol. If two of them move to mitochondria via malate-aspartate
shuttle and four via glycerol-3-phosephate shuttle, how many ATP will be obtained?
A. 10
B. 12
C. 14
D. 16
E. 18
14
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Academic 75
60. According to Lab 3 : DNA isolation, which of the following is used for DNA dilution?
A. Tris EDTA Buffer
B. EDTA Tris Bisulfite
C. Saline Citrate Buffer
D. Tris Borate EDTA Buffer
E. Tris Acetate EDTA Buffer
61. What is turnover number?
A. K1
B. K
-1
C. Kcat
D. Vmax
E. Km
62. A researcher wants to purify protein X (weight= 20 kDa , pI=12) at physiological condition using ion
exchange chromatography and gel filtration chromatography. Which fraction contains the most purified
protein?
A. Tris EDTA Buffer
B. EDTA Tris Bisulfite
C. Saline Citrate Buffer
D. Tris Borate EDTA Buffer
E. Tris Acetate EDTA Buffer
15
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Academic 75
63. Which enzyme has the maximum Kcat number?
A. A, B
B. A, C
C. B, E
D. D, E
E. ไม่ทราบเพราะไม่รู้ MW
64. Which of the following best describes the transfer of protein antigen to membrane to analyse gene
expression?
A. Electrophoresis
B. Eastern Blotting
C. Western Blotting
D. Northern Blotting
E. Southern Blotting
65. Both Dansyl Chloride and PITC have the following properties, except?
A. Quantify amount of amino acids
B. Initiate Edman Degradation reaction
C. React with alpha-amino group of amino acid
D. Determine the amino acid sequences from N to C terminus
E. Identify amino acid at the amino-terminus of polypeptide chains
66. Trypsin is a protease that breaks the bonds at the C-terminus of Arginine and Lysine. This is fully due to
the interaction at the binding pocket of the enzyme. Which amino acid allows for this specific interaction?
A. Histidine
B. Aspartic acid
C. Glutamine
D. Tyrosine
E.
16
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
67. 68. 69. 70. Academic 75
Which of the following regarding enzyme catalytic mechanism is correct?
A. Increase enthalpy of the substrate
B. Increase entropy of the transition state
C. Increase activation energy of the transition state
D. Reduce Gibbs free energy of the reaction
E. Increase rate of reaction without altering the equilibrium
Which of the following complex carbohydrate is used to classify bacteria by Gram staining?
A. Glycolipid
B. Glycoprotein
C. Proteoglycan
D. Peptidoglycan
E. Lipoprotein
Which of the following is a unique characteristics of eukaryotic cell?
A. Circular DNA
B. Polyribosome
C. Maturing RNA
D. Coupling of transcription and translation
E. DNA replication
A partially purified cell extract consists of mitochondria (1.19 g/cm3), lysosome (1.12 g/cm3), and
peroxisome (1.23 g/cm3). If a researcher wants to purified lysosome by using density gradient
centrifugation, which of the following fractions should be collected?
A. Fraction A
B. Fraction B
C. Fraction C
D. Between fraction A and B
E. Between fraction B and C
17
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
71. 72. 73. 74. 75. Academic 75
Which is correct regarding DE0 < 0?
A. Exergonic
B. Exothermic
C. Activate ATP Synthesis
D. Accept electron better than H ion
E. Better reducing agent than H ion
How does an uncompetitive inhibitor bind?
A. Binds to free enzymes
B. Bind reversibly
C. Binds covalently
D. Binds both to free and substrate-bound enzymes
E.
Compared to conventional fluorescence microscopy, what makes confocal microscopy to be extraordinary
tool for living cell study?
A. It can study intracellular organelles.
B. It can separate z-axis dimension.
C. It can reduce out-of-focus reflected light.
D.
E. It can be used to study cells from hours to weeks using cell culture food.
Which one has both hydrophobic and hydrophilic in its structure?
A. phosphatidylcholine
B.
C.
D.
E.
A student dilutes a solution by 10 folds and measure its absorbance (A = 1.532). The result is obviously
higher than most students’ results. Which factor definitely did not cause the error?
A. Fingerprint on cuvette
B. Dilution error
C. Forgot to set blank
D. Pipetting error
E. Did not adjust the wavelength to λmax
18
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
76. 77. 78. Academic 75
Which substance use for dissolving DNA before absorption?
A. Tris-EDTA
B.
C.
D.
E.
As shown in the O2 consumption graph, which of the following is the most likely inhibited by substance X?
A. Complex I
B. Complex II
C. Complex IV
D. F0 of ATP Synthase
E. F1 of ATP Synthase
Which types of inhibitors are X and Y?
A. Y is competitive inhibitor.
B. X is competitive inhibitor.
C. Y is uncompetitive inhibitor.
D. X is uncompetitive inhibitor.
E. X is non-competitive inhibitor.
19
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Academic 75
79. Components in which of the following should give positive for both ninhydrin and orcinol test?
A. Ribosome
B. Hyaluronan
C. Microfilament
D. Nucleosome
E. SER membrane
80. What type of enzymes are FMS and FES?
A. Oxidoreductase
B. Transferase
C. Ligase
D. Isomerase
E. Hydrolase
81. Which of the following is the most logical sequence of steps for adding reagents in the experiment of DNA
isolation?
I. Ethanol
II. NaCl
III. SOS
IV. Chloroform
A. I, IV, III, II
B. II, III, IV, I
C. III, II, IV, I
D. IV, II, I, III
E. II, I, III, IV
82. ข้อใดคือประโยชน์ของ immersion oil?
A. increase contrast
B. decrease reflected light
C. increase magnification and contrast
D. Isomerase
E. increase numerical aperture ทำให้เพิ่ม resolution
83. กล้องจุลทรรศน์ใดไม่มีการเพิ่ม contrast?
A. stereomicroscope
B. DIC
C.
D.
E.
20
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Academic 75
84. What process or reaction converts the monosaccharide derivatives to N-actetylneumuramic acid (Sialic acid)?
A. Oxidation
B. Reduction
C. Phosphorylation
D. Amination
E. Glycosidic formation
85. Which of the following is a common feature found in fluorescence microscope and confocal microscope?
A. Pinhole
B. Exciter filter
C. Dichroic mirror
D. Fluorescent lightsource
E. Automated image processing
86. Which statement CANNOT be inferred from this diagram showing similar domains in proteins A-E?
A
B
C
D
E
A. All proteins are related by evolution.
B. Protein A is different from protein C in structure more than protein B.
C. Each protein’s activity is related to binding Cu2+ ions.
D. Protein C, D, E have similar tertiary structure
E. Protein B has special structure and function because of proline-rich domain.
87. ตามตารางต่อไปนี้ การทดลองใดมีค่า %CV สูงที่สุด?
การทดลอง A B C D E
𝑥̅ S 7 30 40 10 50 60 6 12 9
90
A. Experiment A
B. Experiment B
C. Experiment C
D. Experiment D
E. Experiment E
21
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Academic 75
88. Which of the following is correct to the thermodynamics law?
A. 1st law: energy is unchanged in isolated system.
B. 1st law: spontaneous reaction happens when DG is negative.
C. 2nd law: closed system in nature can change all heat into other energy form.
D. 2nd law: reactions in nature are mostly reversible.
E. 3rd law: at absolute T, enthalpy is negative.
89. Which of the following is not the advantages of self assembly?
A. Small genome
B. Subunit recycling
C. Multiple regulation
D. Strong and rigid structure
E. Reduction of error synthesizing
90. Which of the following is correct to the thermodynamics law?
A. 1st law: energy is unchanged in isolated system.
B. 1st law: spontaneous reaction happens when DG is negative.
C. 2nd law: closed system in nature can change all heat into other energy form.
D. 2nd law: reactions in nature are mostly reversible.
E. 3rd law: at absolute T, enthalpy is negative.
91. Oseltamivir เป็นยาต้านไวรัสไข้หวัดใหญ่ มีชื่อการค้าว่า Tamiflu มีโครงสร้างคล้ายสารใด?
A. Neuraminidase
B. Hemoagglutinin
C. N-Acetylglutamic acid
D. N-Acetylmuramic acid
E. N-Acetylneuraminic acid
92. คลอดก่อนกำหนดมีอาการ tadypnea หายใจไม่สะดวก ขาดสารใด?
A. Ceramide
B. Ganglioside
C. Cardiolipin
D. Sphingomyelin
E. Dipalmitoyl lecitin
22
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Academic 75
93. %T=20, E1g%=8.5, log 2=0.3, dilute 100 เท่า?
A. 0.08
B. 4.xx
C. 8.xx
D. 12.xx
E. 16.xx
94. กรดใดออกทางลมหายใจ?
A. Carbonic acid
B. Aceto…
C. Fatty acid
D. …
E. …
95. Electron Transfer ถูก block อยู่ระหว่าง cyt b กับ cyt c1 ด้วย antimycin A หมายความว่า?
A. An ATP synthesis is stop.
B. P:O ratio is decreased
C. ATP synthesis will continue, P:O will drop to one.
D.
E.
96. แยก DNA ของ bacteriophage ได้ 25% A, 33% T, 24% G, 18% C?
A. The codon is degenerate.
B. The genome in this bacteriophage is single stand.
C. The genome in this bacteriophage is linear and tolerates base mismatch.
D. The genome in this bacteriophage does not follow standard W&C base pairing. It allows wobble
fbase pairing.
E.
97. Which glycosidic inhibit NaKATPase?
A. vinblastin
B. ouabain
C. tamiflu
D. didaosine
E. …
23
--- ##midterm test past paper ---
Academic 75
24
